(music)
PETRAEUS: Kim Jong-Un is the sun around which everything revolves in North Korea.
He has proven to be a very ruthless, impulsive and cruel leader.
with those who pose a threat to the state
and is therefore a threat to him.
NARRATOR: At just 28 years old, Kim Jong-Un became the leader of his country,
the third man to rule North Korea.
He took over his father's nuclear weapons program and supercharged it.
MADDEN: North Korea's Ballistic Missile and Nuclear Weapons Achievements
are the result of Kim Jong-Un's characteristics as a leader.
He far surpassed the lifetime achievements of his father and grandfather.
JERROLD: You can't understand this man without analyzing the family.
where he was born and the impact his grandfather had on him.
READ: Sitting down with the President of the United States is something his father and grandfather
they could never do.
NARRATOR: In charge of the world's fourth largest military, who is Kim Jong-Un?
This is the story of how the younger Kim took control of his country and used the legacy
of his family to position himself on the world stage.
(melancholic music)
(music continues)
The sudden death of Kim Jong-Il, the second man to lead the country
shook the North Korean people.
The future of this corrupt state was a global concern.
and became the top priority for the then CIA director.
PETRAEUS: What I remember in particular was the uncertainty
of what Kim Jong-Un would be like as a leader.
I was quite young, under thirty, I had no experience,
He was said to be impulsive and a little stubborn.
What would you do about the nuclear program, the missile program?
So those factors together gave us something to think about,
that's how we felt at that moment.
NARRATOR: North Korea was a unique state, a communist country,
but under the control of a family.
It was founded by Kim Jong-Un's grandfather, who outlived all other dictators.
communists, before handing over his eldest son, Kim Jong-Un's father.
His untimely death at the age of 70 meant that there was little succession planning.
before Kim Jong-Un was brought to power.
And the CIA wanted to know who he was.
PETRAEUS: Material like this is always observed and analyzed.
Experts were working on it trying to find something, but there is no solid basis.
real since trying to do a psychoanalysis of someone like him,
about whom we had so little information, it was practically impossible.
NARRATOR: One reason the intelligence agency's files were lacking
of details was because Kim Jong-Un was not always the obvious successor.
His father had five recognized children, one of whom was a daughter,
but there are no known photographs of her.
Her youngest son was also a woman, but North Korea was not ready for a female leader.
Of the three known sons, Kim Jong-Nam was the eldest,
and at some point it seemed like a good option.
REPORTER: Are you Mr. Kim Jong-Nam?
KIM JONG-NAM: If you're not sure, why are you following me?
NARRATOR: In the early 2000s, he left North Korea for China,
an event that left him out of the discussion.
The next son, Kim Jong-Chul, had no interest in politics,
and preferred to play guitar in a band.
REPORTER: Why are you in London, Mr. Kim?
NARRATOR: He has been a solitary figure ever since.
has been seen abroad at rock concerts.
MAN: Believed to be Kim Jong-Chol.
He is seen smiling while enjoying a concert
by Eric Clapton at the Royal Albert Hall in London.
NARRATOR: Which left Kim Jong-Un for the role.
Third in line for the throne, and the only choice
to continue the family dynasty.
LEE: My first impression was how vulnerable she was.
But I wondered, "Is that pain tinged with fear?"
It is not simply taking the leadership of a rich country
and surrounded by comforts,
It is a country with a food shortage,
there is no electricity,
and is isolated from the outside world
It's not an easy job to take on.
I was the first American journalist to work for the local press in Pyongyang.
I was able to talk to the North Koreans about what they were being told about who that young man was,
at least in terms of propaganda.
We were told that Kim Jong-Un would be very different from his father,
more like his grandfather who was legitimately loved by his people
and was extremely charismatic.
He wanted to show people that he was a human person, like his grandfather.
He would often sit on the floor, put the children on his lap and hug them.
That's a great strategy: molding him in the image of his grandfather.
It turns out he looks a lot like his grandfather, and that helps.
By adding all the accessories like the straw hat,
which is identical to the hat his grandfather used to wear,
and replicate his walk, the North Koreans would remember him.
That's one way Kim Jong-Un builds on his grandfather's legacy.
to legitimize his role as leader.
NARRATOR: Kim Jong-Un was willing to use the divine status of his father and grandfather,
but he wanted to be the god of the 21st century, showing
to the North Korean people a sense of modernity.
READ: His campaign to show that he was a different kind of leader
It also included showing his wife in public.
That was very significant because his father rarely went out in public,
We didn't know who his wife was because he never introduced his family.
Now they saw Kim Jong-Un's wife, who was beautiful and elegant.
That's powerful in a society like this, which encourages
people to show a little more individualism.
NARRATOR: Some of the intelligence agencies attributed this type
of modern opening to Kim's formative years outside North Korea.
As a teenager, he spent nine years at a school in Switzerland.
After Kim Jong-Un became leader,
Media interest was focused on that moment,
and the news agencies quickly interviewed
to his former colleagues to gain any kind of perspective.
MAN: Most of the time he was shy, quiet and a quiet boy,
But when we played basketball, it came out.
He could be very aggressive, but in a positive way, loud and a little foul-mouthed.
NARRATOR: According to his caretakers in Switzerland, he was so obsessed with the Chicago Bulls
who slept with a basketball next to him.
LEE: I think we're all very curious to know how much time influenced
that Kim Jong-Un spent in Switzerland,
because we think that exposed him to more Western ideas.
And very early in his reign we began to see that.
(music)
It's interesting. He had his own pop group,
a girl band called Moranbong Aktan.
They were a big hit in Pyongyang at the time.
They wore revealing strapless dresses, shorts, miniskirts
and played electric instruments.
We heard them play the theme song from Rocky, which is a very American movie.
So it was all very fresh, very modern and cutting-edge for North Korea.
(applause)
NARRATOR: Kim kept the same military parades established by his father.
and his grandfather, but he used his power to satisfy some
of their own personal interests.
In 2013, he asked one of his heroes to come see him.
RODMAN: My name is Dennis Rodman.
He plays basketball for the Chicago Bulls, Detroit Pistons, and LA Lakers.
I made movies and wrote books.
CNN: It's a great cover and a great headline: "I Should Be Dead By Now."
RODMAN: Whatever I imagined, I already did.
I am that man, Dennis Rodman.
I knew nothing about North Korea.
Something happened in 2013,
The North Korean leader wanted to meet someone from the Chicago Bulls.
And I heard that they had invited Michael Jordan first and he said no, I don't want to go.
So I guess I was the second choice, they said:
"Dennis, would you like to go to North Korea?" I said, "Yeah, sure."
I wasn't worried I thought it was like going to Las Vegas
that would be a crazy trip,
that I would go out with prostitutes, we would go here and there,
we would be in the pool, I thought it would be great, something crazy
I thought, okay, I'll put this trip on my resume.
That's what I thought. I'd go play basketball,
It was all, greet people, take some photos and that was it.
But a big surprise awaited me.
(music)
NARRATOR: Former NBA star Dennis Rodman was about to participate
in the strangest match of his entire career.
RODMAN: I walked into the stadium and then one of the leaders did...
I said, 'What's up?' And he said, 'Why don't you sit over here?'
And I said, "Okay." I didn't know what was going on, I didn't know what was going on.
Then people stood up and started clapping.
(applause)
I thought it was because of me. These people really admire me.
Then I understood, I looked to my left, and thought "is he the one they are applauding for?"
I still didn't know who he was.
(music)
Oh, I remember this.
It was "wow, crazy."
That makes you think, it tells you how powerful this man is.
And this lasted ten or fifteen minutes.
I was doing the same thing as them and I thought
"Who the hell am I applauding for?
I'm an American, I don't know what I'm doing."
So I decided, "You know what, I'm going to join."
I was amazed to see those people crying.
I've seen a lot of strange things in my life, I've met a lot of people, presidents,
I saw many things, but this shocked me.
That's when I began to understand what was happening.
COACH: Team, in threes. One, two, three, yes.
RODMAN: When the game started, he started talking to me.
I didn't know what the hell he was saying. He was speaking Korean.
He kept talking the whole game, he talked the whole game.
I think he's a big fan of American basketball.
and his favorite team is the Chicago Bulls.
We hit it off right away, and we chatted, and we laughed, and he said:
"Whatever you want is yours.
The interpreter said, "Dennis, you are one of the few people who have come to our country
and you are one of the few who have sat next to our leader.
For some reason, he really likes you."
You have been very, very kind to me and my American friends.
Sir, thank you.
We will be friends forever.
Now I was starting to feel more comfortable and I was actually having fun with him,
as if we were friends of many years.
And he said, "Dennis, please, I'd like you to come back sometime.
"I want you to come back whenever you can."
I said, "Okay, I'll come back every three months." And he said, "Yeah, do it."
NEWS: Dennis Rodman is back in North Korea,
and will meet with his friend, dictator Kim Jong-Un.
PRESS: Mr. Rodman is on a private trip and our opinion on North Korea
has not changed.
RODMAN: Hey, I'm not the president, and I'm not a politician.
He's like you, or like him, or like anyone.
She wants to let her hair down and have a good time, that's all.
One day, we are outside smoking cigars, drinking tequila, vodka and I think it was the first
time he told me, you know, I'd like to go to the United States.
He said he wanted to go to the United States to watch a basketball game,
I said to him, "What game do you want to watch?"
He said, "I want to go to Madison Square Garden."
And he said it over and over again, Madison Square Garden."
He did this with his hands and got excited.
I told him: You can do whatever you want.
He replied: "I would love to go but I can't.
"I think a lot of people don't like me."
And I thought, "Wow!"
REPORTER: How was your trip?
RODMAN: It was incredible. REPORTER: Incredible.
Kim, Kim Jong-Un? Tell us about that. How amazing was it?
RODMAN: I have to go through, let me...
(simultaneous dialogue)
WOMAN: Does Dennis Rodman know more about Kim Jong-Un at this point?
than any American? MAN: He is that man.
There's no one in the CIA who can tell you more about Kim Jong-Un than Dennis Rodman.
And that is worrying.
RODMAN: Happy birthday to you.
Happy birthday to you.
Happy birthday dear officer.
(apalusos)
NARRATOR: Rodman's visit to Pyongyang fulfilled a childhood dream for Kim Jong-Un.
But being an all-powerful dictator of the most secretive state on Earth
is not without challenges.
The generals at the heart of the regime were trying to outdo the young Kim,
in an effort to overthrow the inexperienced leader.
But Kim Jong-Un was about to prove that he was just as ruthless.
as the past Kims had been.
(music)
NARRATOR: Kim Jong-Un is a 21st-century dictator.
I was happy to accept certain kinds of progress,
but maintaining complete control is essential,
as well as the loyalty of its inner sanctuary.
READ: One of the things I asked for when I worked as a journalist in North Korea,
was that I was allowed to attend a private meeting.
I wanted to see what things were like behind closed doors.
And you get to see much more than what they show you on television.
They know that when the music plays for Kim Jong-Un
they should stand up and start clapping.
But one of the things I noticed that really caught my attention,
It was that someone didn't stand up and applaud like everyone else did, and it showed.
Jang Song-Thaek sat still.
NARRADOR: Jang Song-Thaek is the son of Jim Jong-Un.
In the early 1970s she married Kim Kyong-Hu,
the only sister of Kim Jong-Un's father.
He joined the family business and thanks to his access to the Kims,
became one of the most powerful figures in the regime.
JONG-YIL: Because of his position within the family,
He was well informed about what was happening within the core of the power structure.
But he was also aware of what was happening outside the family.
Jang Song-Thaek was the second man in the power hierarchy in North Korea.
He was a man of great ability, a very competent man, but also charming.
READ: He was almost always behind Kim Jong-Un whenever he was seen in public.
He was an interesting person. He had been educated in Russia,
so he was exposed to the rest of the world more than Kim.
He also had good relations with China, so he was someone who established
many connections to the world.
That may have been seen by Kim Jong-Un as suspicious and provocative.
JONG-YIL: There were rumors that he had plotted together with China's top leader
replace Kim Jong-Un with his half-brother.
In any kind of tyranny you must constantly monitor who represents a danger.
for the safety of your throne.
NARRATOR: Uncle Jang continued traveling to and from China.
But in December 2013, at a government meeting in Pyongyang,
He realized that his role within the party was over.
JONG-YIL: At the party meeting, even those close to him denounced him.
for having committed serious crimes against the state, against the leader.
They took him away and then arrested him.
His face showed signs of torture.
The guards were chosen with special care.
They loomed before him, tall, carefully coordinated and organized,
This is to get rid of any kind of persistent illusion about
Jang Song-Thaek.
I think the regime was trying to humiliate and degrade him.
NARRATOR: An article in the state newspaper listed crimes such as gambling
state funds, embezzlement, and even adultery.
Jang was not allowed to mount a Defense.
It was all a rigged trial, and the judges made a quick decision.
JONG-YIL: He was sentenced to death, and it was carried out immediately.
NEWS: Kim Jong-Un's uncle has been executed.
TODD: The official report from the North Korean news agency called his uncle
"despicable human scum worse than a dog."
JONG-YIL: We know that Jang Song-Thaek was executed with an anti-aircraft machine gun,
which did not leave many traces of him.
His remains were completely destroyed, so nothing of him remains in this world.
LEE: It certainly didn't just give me chills,
but also provoked them in the government elites.
That served to show that no one was untouchable.
(music)
NARRATOR: Kim punctuated the performance with a new song performed
by North Korea's favorite all-girl band.
(music)
BAEK: Every image, everything people are exposed to is crafted.
There are contracted artists and contracted musicians
who are supported by the government to produce works of art,
music, poetry, everything to support this great production, this great show.
(music)
That says North Korea is the largest country in the world,
and the members of the Kim Dynasty are the gods who rule the North Koreans.
(music)
(applause)
NARRATOR: Kim wanted his people to accept the new vision.
of a 21st-century North Korea.
But this wasn't really optional.
Express any doubts about Kim, the regime, or try to contact the outside world
It was a fatal mistake.
In the early years of Kim's reign, the rate of public executions tripled.
BAEK: In executions they are shot three times, usually in the head,
the chest and stomach.
BAEK: They're tied up so they can't run or move.
But the idea is that if someone gets shot, especially in the stomach,
just leans.
BAEK: Some of my North Korean friends who have seen executions
They say it's crazy that even at the moment of his death a North Korean person
is forced to bow to the state.
BAEK: From the moment someone is born, until they are killed,
It's all in the name of the Kim family.
(music)
READ: There is a story in ancient Korean history that most people know,
It is the story of the first king of the Joseon Dynasty.
He had several children, and when the time came to hand over power,
He chose one and that caused a rivalry.
One of them ended up killing the other.
That parable is known as the Hamheung-chasa.
When I heard the story, I had a very strange feeling in my body because I thought
that in stories about brothers competing for the throne and fratricide
within the family, it is part of how they have governed.
NARRATOR: The Kim family is about to add a 21st-century chapter.
to the legendary stories of Korean dynasties.
Kim Jong-Un had an older half-brother, Kim Jong-Nam,
who was his father's first son,
and a man who was never afraid to speak his mind.
MADDEN: I became interested in North Korea about ten years ago,
I studied a specialty in North Korean politics by collecting information.
There are a lot of people with a lot at stake in North Korea, and I'm in contact with them.
REPORTER: Is your father Mr. Kim Jong-Il?
KIM JONG-NAM: I think that's a ridiculous question. REPORTER: Yes. Sorry.
MADDEN: Kim Jong-Nam studied in Europe for about ten years,
and absorbed certain aspects of Western culture
that are not necessarily aligned with priorities
North Korean policies.
NARRATOR: Kim Jong-Nam used a fake passport to travel the world,
but was caught entering Japan on his way to Tokyo Disneyland.
A great embarrassment to the family, and the beginning of a bitter breakup.
MADDEN: Kim Jong-Nam left North Korea in the early 2000s,
That did not prevent Kim Jong-Nam from having a certain power base.
and that he had links with certain North Korean elites,
but it did remove him from the routine of the North Korean regime.
And if you become the successor, you simply cannot be removed from office.
NARRATOR: As the eldest son, Kim Jong-Nam used to express
their views on North Korea and its future.
From a new base in China, he spoke to reporters, but made sure his location
was hidden so its whereabouts were unknown.
NARRATOR: In 2011, Kim Jong-Nam agreed to a more in-depth interview,
in the Asian gaming capital, Macau.
NARRATOR: Their communication continued via email.
Kim Jong-Nam was clearly not in favor of perpetuating the Kim dynasty.
When Kim Jong-Un became leader, this correspondence gained importance.
and Gomi asked permission to publish his private emails.
NARRATOR: Later that year, South Korean intelligence claimed
having intercepted a message written by Kim Jong-Un.
CCTV footage shows Kim Jong-Nam arriving
to Kuala Lumpur Airport entering the departure hall.
Two women emerge from nowhere, each carrying the nerve agent component VX.
They both rub their hands on his face, combining the chemicals and creating a deadly poison.
In desperation, Kim Jong-Nam calls for help,
but just a few minutes later, he's dead.
CNN: South Korea said it is very likely that North Korea will
is behind this cold-blooded murder.
READ: We don't know if it was an order issued by Kim Jong-Un.
But it is evident that he saw his brother's presence as a threat.
NARRATOR: The murder of his half-brother didn't necessarily stop the criticism.
within the Kim family.
CNN: Nearly a month after North Korean dictator's half-brother was poisoned
At Kuala Lumpur airport, this video appeared
which showed the son of the murdered man, Kim Han Sol.
KIM HAN SOL: My name is Kim Han Sol, I am from North Korea and part of the Kim family.
Here's my passport.
READ: He is a young man under 30 years old and still has his whole life ahead of him.
It is very promising according to what those who know him say,
but maybe he's doomed to run away for the rest of his life
because he represents a potential threat to the throne.
He is a member of the Kim family and has that blood.
KIM HAN SOL: My father was murdered a few days ago.
I now live with my mother and sister.
And we hope this ends soon, yes.
NARRATOR: The murder of his half-brother and the execution of his uncle
meant that Kim Jong-Un could make some changes in his inner circle.
He brought his younger sister and gave her a key role in the party's Politburo.
The young leader's next step was to raise his profile on the world stage.
And he achieved this with a series of missile launches,
showing the regime's growing military capabilities.
CNN: North Korea launched a long-range rocket...
NEWS: Another rocket launched this weekend...
COREN: It's North Korea showing off to the United States
which is a force to be reckoned with.
NARRATOR: Kim was provoking the United States.
That was a move straight out of the family playbook.
But for Kim Jong-Un, this tactic seemed to backfire.
NARRATOR: Just when it seemed that Kim Jong-Un had taken North Korea
to a diplomatic area,
¡USA! ¡USA! ¡USA!
NARRATOR: A new politician entered the race.
NARRATOR: Kim Jong-Un had spent his first five years
al mando purgando su santuario interno de las voces dissidentes.
NARRATOR: And then, he turned his attention to the international stage.
ABC: Good Morning America. The Most Shocking Surprise in American History:
Donald J. Trump elected as the 45th President of the United States.
¡USA! ¡USA! ¡USA!
(Korean language)
REPORTER: North Korea launched a missile, the first of Trump's term.
NARRATOR: The first months of Trump's presidency were marked by a series of
of launches that culminated on Independence Day with the test of a rocket
able to reach Alaska.
(music) (applause)
The regime called this launch "a gift to the American bastards."
NARRATOR: As Trump made strong statements,
North Korea was about to achieve a crucial breakthrough.
ABC: There is a new North Korean threat: it is testing missiles that could reach
North America, there is great concern.
(Korean language)
NARRATOR: Kim Jong-Un issued a statement, saying that his nuclear missile program
It was complete. I was ready to talk.
He began by visiting his counterpart in South Korea.
After a successful summit, he managed to negotiate a meeting
in Singapore with President Trump.
READ: Remember when we first saw him in 2010 and 2011,
He was a baby-faced young man that no one knew.
He didn't have much credibility.
He is now a leader with a verifiably threatening nuclear arsenal.
That puts him in a very different position when it comes to
to negotiate and interact with other countries.
(music)
RODMAN: I knew things were going to change.
I knew I was the only one but they never wanted to listen to me.
I received many death threats, but I was there protecting everything.
I believe in North Korea.
But today is a great day for everyone—Singapore, Tokyo, China, everyone. It's a great day!
READ: The way North Koreans will see it is that this small country with so little
It is so important that its leader was able to sit down with the President of the United States.
That's something his father and grandfather were never able to do.
REPORTER: President Trump, how did it all go?
NARRATOR: Kim Jong-Un had achieved a massive coup,
persuading the leader of the free world to sit down and meet
with him on equal terms.
For over 70 years, grandfather, father, and son
They have convinced North Koreans that they are gods.
(music)
BAEK: For Kim Jong-Un, his country's Achilles' heel
They are the citizens who access foreign information.
BAEK: And so, as more and more citizens listen,
read and watch foreign media,
More and more people are questioning the reality in North Korea,
further question the political legitimacy of the state.
This puts Kim Jong Un in a very dangerous position.
If people stop believing they are gods,
the fundamental belief of that country will be eroded.
Once its political legitimacy diminishes,
will have nothing to stand on.
(music)
NARRATOR: For more than 70 years, the Kim family
has literally kept his people in the dark.
The most secret state on Earth remains separate from the outside world.
The hermit kingdom is still under the rule of one family.
(music)
Subtitles created by SubTitlePro LLC